Guide to the Johan William Colenbrander Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Johan William Colenbrander collection
1860-1998
MS 1460
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2
The collection consists primarily of photocopies of documents and photographs, assembled by Johan Cornelis Alphons Lawrence Colenbrander, which relate to the personal life and professional activities of his father, Johan W. Colenbrander.
Colenbrander, Johan William, 1859-1918
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of J. C. A. L. Colenbrander, 1985-1995, 1998.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Johan William Colenbrander Collection consists of photocopies of documents and photographs, assembled by Johan Cornelis Alphons Lawrence Colenbrander, which relate to the personal life and professional activities of his father, Johan W. Colenbrander. Copied documents include letters written to J. C. A. L. Colenbrander by other family members and acquaintances of J. W. Colenbrander, papers held by archives in Zimbabwe and South Africa, and clippings and other printed material.
J. C. A. L. Colenbrander collected much biographical and genealogical data. Photocopies are bound together according to his arrangement and are extensively annotated with his comments.
J. C. A. L. Colenbrander donated his collection to the Yale Library from 1985 to 1990. He also donated similar materials to Rhodes House at Oxford University, the National Archives of Zimbabwe, and the Kille Campbell Archives in Durban, Natal.
Biographical / Historical
Johan Colenbrander was born in Pinetown, Natal, in 1857. He enlisted with the Natal Mounted Rifles in 1870 and participated in the Zulu War in 1879. Colenbrander was active as a soldier, businessman, interpreter, agent, and hunter in Natal, Swaziland, Bulawayo, and Matabeleland until 1900 when he moved to South Africa to command Kitchener's Fighting Scouts. After the Boer War, Colenbrander was engaged in several unsuccessful business ventures in South Africa, Rhodesia, and Mexico. He died in 1918.
South African War, 1899-1902; South Africa -- History -- 1836-1909; Zimbabwe -- History; Photographs; Soldiers; Colenbrander, Johan Cornelis Alphons Lawrence; Colenbrander, Johan William, 1859-1918
- Inventory
  - J. C. A. L. Colenbrander's correspondence concerning his research on Johan William Colenbrander, 1950-1955, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Family history, 1951-1979 [ca.1984], 1993, 1998, undated [ca.1860-1985] (Box 1, Folder 2-2e)
  - Photographs, [ca. 1860-1985] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Guides to Johan William Colenbrander papers in South Africa, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - J. C. A. L. Colenbrander's collection of documents relating to Johan William Colenbrander: photocopies, [ca.1861-1984] (Box 2, Folder 5 - 9)
  - J. C. A. L. Colenbrander's collection of documents relating to Johan William Colenbrander: photocopies, [ca. 1861-1984] (Box 3, Folder 10 - 13)
  - "The Record of the Court of Inquiry on the Shangani Expedition," photocopy from original in National Archives of Zimbabwe, 1893 December 20 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Additional Material, Accession 1991-M-014
  General note
  See Series I, Box 3, Folder 14
- Additional Material, Accession 1993-M-020
  - Sibebu Ka Mapita: a Study in the Problems of Zulu Leadership in the Years 1879-1884, by P. J. Colenbrander, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Some Reflections on the Kingship of Mpande," by P. J. Colenbrander, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)